All effective communications begin with empathy.
You cannot know where you’re going if you don’t understand where you’re coming from.
And it’s also important to understand where the other person is coming from.
That’s why empathy is so important.
At a high level, empathy is the ability to understand — or at least ask —
what might the other person be thinking or feeling about this topic?
What is important to them?
How might what they’re feeling about the topic influence what’s possible in the meeting or in the interaction?
The mindset of an effective communicator is one that I always describe as “over there”.
Think of it in terms of “over there” versus “over here”.
Let’s say, for example, when I’m “over here”, I’m wrapped up thinking about my own agenda,
worried about my own timelines, my own goals, my own needs.
I’m really caught up in my own inner dialogue and not really taking into account the other person or what they have in mind.
But when I’m in an “over there” mindset, I’m actually open and curious and interested in what they may be thinking or feeling about the topic.
And therefore we can have a really better, more nuanced conversation,
where it’s much more inclusive and engaging and hopefully leads to real action.
Great listening is such an important part of being an effective communicator.
Great listening is about being present, being genuinely interested and curious about what the other person has to say,
asking questions to better understand their perspective, and really listening for what the other person is saying — and maybe not saying.
You can even recognise when you’re not doing it.
Say you’re rushing between meetings, calls and deadlines.
You arrive at your next meeting still processing the last one, and your phone beeps with a text message:
“Where’s the report for Janine? She needs it in two hours.” — “In a meeting.”
You’re not really listening to what the other person is saying.
You may be planning what you want to say next rather than really listening to the other person.
People can tell when it is an asynchronous conversation, and that you’re not really present.
And at that point, what’s the point of even talking?
A lot of times, if you do have even just a minute before a meeting: stop, think and pause.
Take a few deep breaths.
Focus on thinking about the other person,
and remind yourself to keep an open mind as to what the agenda might look like and how the conversation might go.
Sometimes that can make it a little bit easier to more naturally fall into an “over there” mindset.
We’ve discussed what empathy is and what it is not,
and next we will look at why empathy matters.
This isn’t the end of the conversation when it comes to empathy.
Empathy is going to weave itself throughout this course and in every step of the process,
because it’s important that we constantly revisit how our audience — how the other person — is thinking and feeling as we’re creating and developing any kind of interaction.